<section xml:id="ethics-arbitrage-and-insider-training">
	<title>Ethics Case Study -- Arbitrage and Insider Trading</title>
	<p>
		Recall that arbitrage is a risk-free profit.  Note that we factor the time-value of money in our understanding of profit.  At the beginning of this chapter, we saw how an assumption that there is no arbitrage is used to value annuities.  Later in this book, and in later courses, you will see that an assumption that there is no arbitrage is used to price cash flows and other forms of investments. The assumption that there is no arbitrage is considered reasonable, as if an arbitrage opportunity arises the market will adapt. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="ethical-problem-of-arbitrage">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				According to Timothy Johnson, the assumption that there is no arbitrage is taken to be an ethical principle.  Explain -- why would the presence of arbitrage be an ethical problem?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<p>
		One of the ways one can find an arbitrage opportunity is by obtaining <term>inside information</term>.  This is sometimes legal and sometimes illegal, and insider trading laws are enforced by the Securities and Exchange Commission.  While not defined by statute, the courts describe insider trading as "purchasing or selling a security while in possession of material, non-public information concerning that security, where the information is obtained from a breach of fiduciary duty, or a duty arising from a relationship of trust or confidence." 
	</p>
	<p>
		One can imagine trading based on stolen inside information as an illegal activity. 
	</p>
	<p>
		In the movie <pubtitle>Trading Places</pubtitle>, the heroes get revenge on the antagonists by co-opting the antagonists' insider trading scheme, engaging in insider trading themselves, and make a great deal of money while bankrupting the antagonists.  While the audience feels some satisfaction, the heroes actually engaged in insider trading. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Suppose you are an SEC prosecutor, and you have to decide whether to prosecute the heroes in this case.  There is room to exercise prosecutorial discretion.  Keep in mind that the underlying ethical principal is the no arbitrage assumption.
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="analyzing-trading-places-problem-statement">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 1</em>: State the problem.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<p>
		The heroes of the movie are Louis Winthorp III and Billy Ray Valentine.  Louis is a wealthy managing director at an investment brokerage owned by the antagonists, the Duke brothers, and Billie Ray is a homeless beggar.  Louis is played by Dan Akroyd and Billie Ray is played by Eddie Murphy. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The Duke brothers are debating whether nature or nurture has a greater impact on whether a person is successful (materially).  To resolve the debate, they engage in an experiment where they arrange to switch Louis and Billie Ray.  The brothers actually bet over the outcome.  They frame Louis for theft, and plant illegal drugs on him.  He gets arrested, loses his job, loses his house, his money, and his fiance.  He ends up moving in with a prostitute.  The Dukes then hire Billie Ray and provide him with a home, a servant, a job in their firm (with training), a car, clothes, etc.  Louis ends up trying to rob the Duke's firm, while Billie Ray ends up successfully managing the firm.  This leads the Dukes to determine the experiment was a success, and the bet is paid up (for one dollar!). 
	</p>
	<p>
		Billie Ray overhears the Duke brothers discussing the experiment (and making racist comments).  He tracks Louis down and explains what happened.  The two of them team up to get revenge by making themselves wealthy while making the Duke brothers poor. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Their plan involves a secret USDA crop report, projecting orange crop yields for the coming season.  The Duke brothers have hired someone to steal a copy of the crop report in order to take over the "frozen concentrated orange juice" commodity market.  Louis and Billie Ray find out about this, and decide that they are going to steal the actual crop report and switch it with a fake crop report that contains the opposite results.  The conclusion of the actual report is that the crop yields should be normal, while the fake report concludes that the cold weather will reduce the crop yields.  This is important, because if crop yields reduce, the supply curve shifts and makes frozen concentrated orange juice more expensive on the commodity market. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="analyzing-trading-places-gathering-facts">
		<introduction>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 2</em>: Gather the facts. Louis and Billie Ray use the real crop report to get rich and the fake crop report leads the Duke brothers to lose their money by trading in Frozen Concentrated Orange Juice futures (futures are standardized and trade-able contracts to buy or sell something at a fixed price at a fixed time in the future).  Part of their plan involves "short-selling" futures.  If the typical way to make a profit on a commodity or stock market is by buying low and then selling high (this is called "going long"), then short selling is the opposite: sell high first, then buy low (to "cover the position"). 
			</p>
			<p>
				Watch the following two videos and answer the questions that follow.
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="end-of-trading-places">
				<caption>End of the movie <pubtitle>Trading Places</pubtitle>. Some strong language.</caption>
				<video youtube="RLySXTIBS3c"/>
			</figure>
			<figure xml:id="explanation-of-end-of-trading-places">
				<caption>An explanation of the end of <pubtitle>Trading Places</pubtitle>. Some strong language.</caption>
				<video youtube="Aa5-CsWLGu8"/>
			</figure>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Explain how Louis and Billie Ray created an arbitrage opportunity.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Explain the role insider trading played in the creation of the arbitrage opportunity.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Why might the audience typically think that their action is justified?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="analyzing-trading-places-identify-stakeholders">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 3</em>: Identify stakeholders.  Consider both primary stakeholders (directly affected) and secondary stakeholders (indirectly affected).  Try to see the situation through the eyes of all possible stakeholders.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="analyzing-trading-places-developing-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 4</em>: Develop options.  Be imaginative, avoid dilemmas or yes/no situations. Instead consider how to modify questions and ask “to/for whom” or “how much."
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="analyzing-trading-places-test-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 5</em>: Test options by determining how the stakeholders you identified are harmed or benefited by an action or inaction.  Test at least two options by filling in the following tables.  You can add rows for more stakeholders, and make additional tables for more options. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<em>Option 1</em>:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Stakeholder
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Primary or Secondary?
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Harms
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Benefits
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<line>

							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="analyzing-trading-places-make-decision">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 6</em>: Make a decision.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="analyzing-trading-places-check-work">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 7</em>: Check your work!  Make sure your decision follows your gut instincts and your internal principles.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="trading-places-memo">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Write a memo to a superior in the SEC prosecutor recommending action.  Be sure to support your position and address counterarguments (see outline in <xref ref="ethics-student-loans-and-covid"/>).
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>