<section xml:id="financial-interpretation-annuities-perpetuities">
	<title>A Financial Interpretation of <m>s_{\angln}</m></title>
	<p>
		So far, we derived the formula for <m>a_{\angln}</m> and used that formula and our work with timelines to obtain the formulas for <m>a_{\angl{\infty}}</m> and <m>s_{\angln}</m>.  
	</p>
	<p>
		In this section, we are going to use timeline reasoning and financial intuition to find the formulas for <m>a_{\angl\infty}</m> and <m>s_{\angln}</m> (and thereby, for <m>a_{\angln}</m>).
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="financial-interpretation-perpetuity">
		<introduction>
			<p> 
				We begin with perpetuities.  Perpetuities can be thought of as paying the interest off on a loan, and only the interest, forever.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Suppose we borrow <m>P</m> at an annual interest rate <m>\iota</m>, and pay the interest off (and no principal) annually forever.  The annual payment is <m>K</m>.  Write a formula for <m>K</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Solve this formula for <m>P</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Which variable in this formula is actually <m>Ka_{\angl\infty}</m>?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="using-perpetuities-to-examine-annuities">
		<introduction>
			<p>
				We are now going to use perpetuities to examine annuities.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Suppose we have two perpetuities with payments of <m>K</m>.  Perpetuity 1 starts making payments at the end of the first year, and Perpetuity 2 starts making payments at the end of year <m>n+1</m> (at time <m>n+1</m>).  Both are valued with the same effective interest rate <m>\iota</m>. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Make two timelines - one for each perpetuity.  Include times 0, 1, 2, <m>n</m>, <m>n+1</m>, and <m>n+2</m> in both timelines.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Make a new timeline representing what we would get if we subtracted the Perpetuity 2 payments from Perpetuity 1 (subtract the payments at each point in time).
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				What does your new timeline represent financially?  
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Find the value at time <m>n</m> of Perpetuities 1 and 2, then subtract and simplify.  What do we get?  Do you recognize this?
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Find any missing annuity immediate or perpetuity immediate formulas.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Could you see using this approach to reconstruct annuity-immediate formulas if you do not remember them?  Why or why not?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
</section>


