<section xml:id="ethics-student-loans-and-covid">
	<title>Ethics Case Study -- Student Loans and COVID-19</title>
	<p>
		As the Biden administration prepared to take office in early 2021, there were calls to forgive outstanding federal student loans. There have been calls for federal loan forgiveness for years based on the increasing volume of outstanding student loans.  This was dubbed the "student loan crisis," which was made significantly worse by the COVID-19 pandemic and the economic consequences. 
	</p>
	<p>
		There were those, however, who argued that student loan forgiveness is not appropriate.  Their argument was an ethical one -- you should pay back what you borrowed. 
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="student-loans-ethics-case-study">
		<introduction>
			<p>
				In this case study, we will examine student loan forgiveness using a framework for ethical reasoning. We will use this framework regularly to perform ethical reasoning throughout this book.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				<em>Step 1</em>: State the problem.  Frame the problem that we are going to investigate.  We may come back and change this as we proceed.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 2</em>: Gather the facts.  Data displayed on the following page are from the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis is displayed below, showing total outstanding student loans (in billions) over time (measured quarterly) between 2006 and 2020.  By 2020, there were over 44 million student loan borrowers. 
			</p>
			<p>
				What does this figure tell you? What additional questions do you have?  Find additional information as necessary.  Use space on this and the following page to record your findings.
			</p>
			<figure xml:id="outstanding-student-loans">
				<caption>Outstanding student loans in billions of dollars from 2006 to 2020.</caption>
				<image source="images/sloans.png">
					Graph showing a steady rise in outstanding student loans from approximately 500 billion dollars in 2006 to over 1.7 trillion dollars in 2020.
				</image>
			</figure>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 3</em>: Identify stakeholders.  Consider both primary stakeholders (directly affected) and secondary stakeholders (indirectly affected).  Try to see the situation through the eyes of all possible stakeholders.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 4</em>: Develop options.  Be imaginative, avoid dilemmas or yes/no situations. Instead consider how to modify questions and ask “to/for whom” or “how much."
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 5</em>: Test options by determining how the stakeholders you identified are harmed or benefited by an action or inaction.  Test at least two options by filling in the following tables.  You can add rows for more stakeholders, and make additional tables for more options. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<em>Option 1</em>:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Stakeholder
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Primary or Secondary?
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Harms
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Benefits
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<line>
								     
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 6</em>: Make a decision.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 7</em>: Check your work!  Make sure your decision follows your gut instincts and your internal principles.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="student-loan-memo">
		<introduction>
			<p> 
				Write a memo setting forth and defending a recommendation to the Biden administration.  Be sure to address harms and benefits to stakeholders. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Outline your memo as follows:
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p> 
				State your recommendation. Be sure to include background information and why the issue is important.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Address counterarguments.  Before going through your argument, address arguments against your position.  Present counterarguments fairly and objectively.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				State your arguments.  Provide support from your stakeholder analysis for each supporting argument.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Conclusion. Restate your recommendation and describe implications.  Do not include new information.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
</section>