<section xml:id="ethics-reserve-requirements">
	<title>Ethics Case Study: Reinsurance and Catastrophe Bonds</title>
	<p>
		In this chapter, we have looked at simple models for reserving. Reserving is a major part of an insurer’s strategy for making sure they have the assets to pay claims as they come due. Insurers also include plans for unusually large claims, often through <term>risk transfer</term>. Risk transfer is a process by which a financial risk is taken on by another person or organization for a price. Standard insurance is a form of risk transfer.
	</p>
	<p>
		Typically, the transfer of risk for rare and very large claims involves something called reinsurance. When it comes to property and casualty insurance, there are also catastrophe bonds for events such as Category 5 hurricanes or significant wildfires. In this case study, we will describe what these are, read a note about the reinsurance and catastrophe bond markets, and evaluate these options ethically using our ethical reasoning skills.
	</p>
	<p>
		Let’s start with reinsurance. <term>Reinsurance</term> is an insurance policy sold to insurance companies that reimburses the insured for claims in excess of a set amount. Reinsurance policies are available from firms that specialize in the product, such as Swiss RE.
	</p>
	<p>
		<term>Catastrophe bonds</term> are another form of risk transfer, where the risk is taken on by investors. When a catastrophe bond is issued, the funds raised by the issuer are placed in a special, isolated, interest-bearing account. Coupon payments include income on the funds plus a premium paid by the issuer. If the event insured against occurs (the <term>trigger event</term>), the raised funds are released to the issuer and the investors lose their investment. Otherwise, at the end of the term, the funds are returned to the investors as a redemption payment. This is kind of like crowdsourced insurance.
	</p>
	<activity>
		<statement>
			<p>
				Read <url href="https://www.irmi.com/articles/expert-commentary/reinsurance-and-catastrophe-bond-trends">the note published by IRMI, the International Risk Management Institute</url>. What do you think of the note? How would you describe the tone?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Let’s evaluate reinsurance and catastrophe bonds using ethical reasoning.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Start with an ethical lens. Revisit the <url href="https://www.scu.edu/ethics/ethics-resources/a-framework-for-ethical-decision-making/">Markkula Center’s website and review the six ethical lenses</url>. Based on the decisions you have made in the ethical case studies in this book, which lens do you think fits you best? Why?
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				With your selected lens in mind, identify at least one ethical issue related to either reinsurance or catastrophe bonds (or both). Explain.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Describe the benefits and harms to stakeholders based on the ethical issue you identified.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				What are some alternative actions that could be taken to address the ethical issue you identified? How do these choices mitigate the harms you identified? How do they preserve the benefits you identified? Do they introduce any new harms or benefits to stakeholders?
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				After evaluating options, decide on a course of action and justify your decision.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Reflect on the decision – does it match the ethical lens you selected? Why or why not?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity>
		<statement>
			<p>
				Write and submit 
			</p>
			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
						A memo recommending and justifying your decision (be sure to identify the issue you noted!),
					</p>
				</li> 
				<li>
					<p>
						A reflection that describes what lens you selected and how your decision does or does not match your choice
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						A brief discussion what you have learned about ethical reasoning in this course.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>