<section xml:id="exact-matching-with-zero-coupon-bonds">
	<title>Exact Matching with Zero-Coupon Bonds</title>
	<p>
		<term>Liabilities</term> are amounts firms owe, and <term>assets</term> are the resources firms have to pay their liabilities.  <term>Exact matching</term> is an investment strategy in which the payouts of the assets occur at the same time the liabilities come due, and in the same amounts.
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="matching-a-liability">
		<statement>
			<p>
				Suppose we have a liability of 1000 coming due at the end of one year.  List at least two possible investments we could purchase now in order to exactly match the liability.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="choosing-zero-coupon-bonds">
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Suppose zero-coupon bonds are the only investments available, and the yield curve is as follows: 
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Year
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							1
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							4
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<m>s_0(t)</m>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							4.00%
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.25%
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							6.00%
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							6.25%
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
			<p>
				For each of the following liability schedules, determine (i) which zero-coupon bonds you will invest in, (ii) how much face value of each zero-coupon bond you will purchase, and (iii) the total cost of the assets to exactly match liabilities.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				There is exactly one liability of 1000 at the end of year 1.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				There is a liability of 1000 due at the end of year 1, and another liability of 1000 due at the end of year 2.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				There is a liability of 2000 due at the end of year 1, and another liability of 3000 due at the end of year 2.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				There is a liability of 1500 due at the end of year 1, a liability of 1000 due at the end of year 2, and a liability of 2000 due at the end of year 3.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				There is a liability of 1000 due at the end of year 1, a liability of 2000 due at the end of year 2, and a liability of 3000 at the end of year 4.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="choosing-interest-rate-to-match-liability">
		<statement>
			<p>
				Suppose we have a liability of 2500 due at the end of year 1 and a liability of 3250 due at the end of year 2.  The effective annual interest rate on a 1-year zero-coupon bond is 4%.  What is the lowest effective annual interest rate you need for a two-year, zero-coupon bond in order to keep the cost of exact matching under 5340.50.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="exact-matching-with-zero-coupon-bonds-reflection">
		<statement>
			<p>
				How do you expect the exact matching cost calculations will change when we use coupon bonds instead of zero-coupon bonds?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>