<section xml:id="ethics-reserve-requirements">
	<title>Ethics Case Study -- Reserve Requirements</title>
	<p>
		We have seen that the purpose of immunization is to make sure a company has sufficient assets to pay off expected liabilities.  For an insurance company, liabilities are uncertain.  They are estimated using expected values for probability distributions (often derived from large data sets using either "Monte-Carlo simulations" or `'bootstrapping").  
	</p>
	<p>
		The assets an insurance company (or any company or investor) hold have varying degrees of uncertainty.  They will likely include a range of investments from risk-free assets such as United States government bonds to low-risk investments such as highly-rated corporate bonds to higher-risk investments in equity markets.  When preparing for later exams, you will learn how this risk is evaluated and how the mix of risk profiles is selected (there is some discretion based on the investors' preferences). 
	</p>
	<p>
		Given the uncertainty in their liabilities, insurance companies may be tempted to include more high-risk assets in their investments.  States impose <term>insurance reserve requirements</term> in order to make sure insurance companies can meet their policyholders' claims as they arise.  Reserves have to be held in either cash or in low-risk investments that are highly liquid (can be converted to cash quickly).  Sometimes this is called <term>unimpaired capital</term>.  In Michigan, the reserve requirements are set by the Department of Insurance and Financial Services, but there is a statutory floor of 7 million (MCL 500.410(2)).  
	</p>
	<p>
		The State of Ferris is a brand new state in the union and is developing its first legal code.  You have been retained by Governor Eisler in order to advise on insurance regulation.  You are thinking about insurance reserves, and before determining standards for required reserves, you want to decide whether this restriction is ethical.
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-problem-statement">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 1</em>: State the Problem.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-fact-gathering">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 2</em>: Gather the Facts.
			</p>
			<p>
				Examine the list of state reserve requirements available at <url href="https://bit.ly/ReservesByState"/>. This list is compiled and maintained by the National Association of Insurance Commissioners.  Do not worry if you don't understand the details.  Summarize what you find.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-identify-stakeholders">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 3</em>: Identify stakeholders.  Consider both primary stakeholders (directly affected) and secondary stakeholders (indirectly affected).  Try to see the situation through the eyes of all possible stakeholders. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-develop-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 4</em>: Develop options.  Be imaginative, avoid dilemmas or yes/no situations. Instead consider how to modify questions and ask “to/for whom” or “how much." 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-test-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 5</em>: Test options by determining how the stakeholders you identified are harmed or benefited by an action or inaction.  Test at least two options by filling in the following tables.  You can add rows for more stakeholders, and make additional tables for more options. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<em>Option 1</em>:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Stakeholder
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Primary or Secondary?
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Harms
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Benefits
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<line>

							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-make-decision">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 6</em>: Make a decision. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-check-work">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 7</em>: Check your work!  Make sure your decision follows your gut instincts and your internal principles.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="reserve-requirements-memo">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Write a memo to Governor Eisler stating your recommendation.  Be sure to support your position and address counterarguments (see outline in <xref ref="ethics-student-loans-and-covid"/>).
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>