<exercises xml:id="matching-liabilities-assets-problems">
	<title>Problems</title>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> A company must pay liabilities of 1000 and 2000 at the end of years 1 and 2, respectively.  The only investments available to the company are the following two zero-coupon bonds: 
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular halign="center" top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Maturity (years)
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Effective annual yield
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Par
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							1
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							10%
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							1000
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							12%
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							1000
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
			<p>
				Determine the cost to the company today to match its liabilities exactly.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> An insurance company accepts an obligation to pay 10,000 at the end of each year for 2 years. The insurance company purchases a combination of the following two bonds at a total cost of <m>X</m> in order to exactly match its obligation:
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<p>
						1-year 4% annual coupon bond with a yield rate of 5%
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						2-year 6% annual coupon bond with a yield rate of 5%
					</p>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				Calculate <m>X</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-broverman"/> Liabilities of 1 each are due at the ends of periods 1 and 2. There are three securities available to produce asset income to cover these liabilities, as follows:
			</p>
			<ol>
				<li>
					<p>
						A bond due at the end of period 1 with coupon rate 1% per period, valued at a periodic yield of 14%.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						A bond due at the end of period 2 with coupon rate 2% per period, valued at a periodic yield of 15%.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						A bond due at the end of period 2 with coupon rate 20% per period, valued at a periodic yield of 14.95%.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
			<p>
				Determine the cost of the portfolio that exactly matches income to liabilities due using:
				\begin{enumerate}
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				bonds (i) and (ii) only.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				bonds (i) and (iii) only.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-broverman"/> A small company terminating its operations has decided to provide each of its three employees with a severance package that pays 10,000 per year (at the end of each year) up to and including age 65, plus a lump sum payment of 100,000 at age 65.  In case of death of an employee before age 65, the payments continue until that employee would have been 65.  The three employees are now exactly ages 50, 53, and 55.  
			</p>
			<p>
				Suppose the company determines that the payments due under this package can be met by the income and maturities generated by three bonds, each with a face amount of 100,000 and an annual coupon rate of 10% and with maturities of 10, 12, and 15 years. Determine the cost to the company to fund the severance package if the bonds have (effective annual) yield rates of 10% for the 10-year bond, 11% for the 12-year bond, and 12% for the 15-year bond.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-broverman"/> Liability payments of 100 each are due to be paid in 2, 4, and 6 years from now.  Asset cashflow consists of <m>A_1</m> in 1 year and <m>A_5</m> in 5 years. The yield for all payments is 10%. An attempt is made to have the asset cash flow immunize the liability cashflow by matching present value and duration.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find <m>A_1</m> and <m>A_5</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Determine whether or not the conditions of Redington immunization are satisfied.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-vaaler-daniel"/> Providence Health Care is obligated to make a payment of 300,000 in exactly three years. In order to provide for this obligation, their financial officer decides to purchase a combination of one-year zero-coupon bonds and four-year zero-coupon bonds. Each of these bonds is sold to yield an effective yield of 4%. How much of each type of bond should be purchased so that the present value and duration conditions of Redington immunization are satisfied? Is the convexity condition also satisfied at <m>\iota = 4\%</m>?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> Trevor has assets at time 2 of <m>A</m> and at time 9 of <m>B</m>. He has a liability of 95,000 at time 5. Trevor has achieved Redington immunization in his portfolio using an annual effective interest rate of 4%. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Calculate <m>\frac{A}{B}</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> A liability consists of a series of 15 annual payments of 35,000 with the first payment to be made one year from now. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The assets available to immunize this liability are five-year and ten-year zero-coupon bonds. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The annual effective interest rate used to value the assets and the liability is 6.2%.  The liability has the same present value and duration as the asset portfolio. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Calculate the amount invested in the five-year zero-coupon bonds.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> Aakash has a liability of 6000 due in four years. The liability will be met with payments of <m>A</m> in two years and <m>B</m> in six years. Aakash is employing a full immunization strategy using an annual effective interest rate of 5%. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Calculate <m>|A-B|</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> Jia Wen has a liability of 12,000 due in eight years. This liability will be met with payments of 5000 in five years and <m>B</m> in <m>8+b</m> years. Jia Wen is employing a full immunization strategy using an annual effective interest rate of 3%. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Calculate <m>\frac{B}{b}</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-kellison"/> A payment of 10,000 is due at time 10. This obligation will be met by payments of <m>A</m> at time 5 and <m>B</m> at time 15. The effective rate of interest is 10% and a full immunization strategy is adopted. Find <m>A</m> and <m>B</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-kellison"/> A payment of 10,000 is due at time 10. This obligation will be met by payments of <m>A</m> at time <m>10 - a</m> and 6000 at time 12.  The effective rate of interest is 10% and a full immunization strategy is adopted.  Find <m>A</m> and <m>a</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-broverman"/> A liability of 1 is due at time 10. An attempt is made to fully immunize this liability at <m>\iota_0 = 0.10</m> using two zero-coupon bonds of amounts <m>A_{t_1}</m> and <m>A_{t_2}</m> due at times <m>t_1</m> and <m>t_2</m> respectively. In each of the following cases, solve for the two missing quantities out of <m>A_{t_1}</m>, <m>A_{t_2}</m>, <m>t_1</m>, <m>t_2</m>, given the other two.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>t_1 = 5</m>, <m>t_2 = 15</m>
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>t_1 = 5</m>, <m>A_{t_1} = 0.40</m>
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>t_1 = 5</m>, <m>A_{t_1} = 0.70</m> 
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> An insurance company has a known liability of 1,000,000 that is due 8 years from now. The technique of full immunization is to be employed. Asset I will provide a cash flow of 300,000 exactly 6 years from now. Asset II will provide a cash flow of <m>X</m>, exactly <m>y</m> years from now, where <m>y > 8</m>. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The annual effective interest rate is 4%. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Calculate <m>X</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				<xref ref="bibliography-soa"/> Which of the following statements about immunization strategies are true? (More than one may be true).
			</p>
			<ol marker="(I)">
				<li>
					<p>
						To achieve immunization, the convexity of the assets must equal the convexity of the liabilities.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						The full immunization technique is designed to work for any change in the interest rate.
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						The theory of immunization was developed to protect against adverse effects created by changes in interest rates.
					</p>
				</li>
			</ol>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
</exercises>