<section xml:id="review-weighted-averages">
	<title>Review -- Weighted Averages</title>
	<p>
		Weighted averages are common in finance as well as actuarial science.  Our first version of duration, a measurement of interest rate risk, will be a weighted average.  You will see many more.
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="weighted-averages-as-shortcuts">
		<statement>
			<p>
				Cobra Kai Dojos Inc. has issued the following quarterly dividends per share over the past two and a half years: 
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Quarter
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							1
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							4
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							6
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							7
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							8
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							9
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							10
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Dividends
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							3.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							3.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							2.50
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
			<p>
				Find a shortcut to calculate the average quarterly dividend per share.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="defining-weighted-average">
		<statement>
			<p>
				For a set of values <m>t_i</m>, <m>i = 1, \ldots, n</m>, the weighted average of the values with weights <m>\omega_i</m> is:
				<me>\sum_{i = 1}^n \omega_i t_i</me>
				where <m>\sum \omega_i = 1</m>. 
			</p>
			<p>
				If you calculate the average quarterly dividend per share of Cobra Kai using a weighted average, what were the weights and what did they represent?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="weighted-gains">
		<statement>
			<p>
				Danny LaRusso has a portfolio with three investments.  The investment values and most recently quarterly gain/loss are:
			</p>
			<ul>
				<li>
					<p>
						Investment A: Value is 15,000, quarterly loss of 150
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Investment B: Value is 22,500, quarterly gain of 275
					</p>
				</li>
				<li>
					<p>
						Investment C: Value is 12,500, quarterly gain of 450
					</p>
				</li>
			</ul>
			<p>
				Find the average gain/loss, weighted by value relative to the portfolio.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="weighted-average-of-cost-of-capital">
		<introduction>
			<p>
				The <term>cost of capital</term> is the return an investor demands in order to invest.  For equity investors, the equity cost of capital is denoted <m>r_E</m> while for debt, the debt cost of capital (think of as the interest rate demanded) is denoted <m>r_D</m>.  
			</p>
			<p>
				If a firm has equity <m>E</m> and debt <m>D</m>, the total value of the firm is <m>D + E</m> and the <term>weighted average cost of capital</term> is:
			</p>
			<me>WACC = \left(\frac{E}{D + E} \right) r_E + \left( \frac{D}{D + E} \right) r_D</me>
			<p>
				Note that the value of <m>D+E</m> is the total value of the firm's assets according to the fundamental accounting equation. 
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Describe the weights in <m>WACC</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Miyagi Do Karate has debt of <m>D = 15000</m> and equity of <m>E = 30000</m>.  They face a debt cost of capital of <m>r_D = 2.25\%</m> and an equity cost of capital of <m>r_E = 6\%</m>.  Find the weighted-average cost of capital.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="weighted-average-reflection">
		<statement>
			<p>
				When will a weighted average have the same value as an ordinary average?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>
