<section xml:id="review-taylor-series-and-approximations">
	<title>Review -- Taylor Series and Approximations</title>
	<p>
		In Calculus, you learn about Taylor series.  The theory tells you that under certain conditions, you write a function "near" a  value <m>x</m> as a polynomial in <m>\Delta x</m>:
	</p>
	<me>f(x + \Delta x) = \sum_{k = 0}^{\infty} \frac{f^{(k)}(x)}{k!}(\Delta x)^k</me>
	<p>
		Here, <m>f^{(k)}(x)</m> stands for the <m>k</m>th derivative (where <m>k = 0</m> corresponds to the original function).  If we write this in expanded notation, this looks like:
	</p>
	<me>f(x+ \Delta x) = f(x) + f'(x)(\Delta x) + \frac{f"(x)}{2}(\Delta x)^2 + \frac{f"'(x)}{6}(\Delta x)^3 + \cdots + \frac{f^{(k)}(x)}{k!}(\Delta x)^k + \cdots</me>
	<p>
		We call this the Taylor series around <m>x</m> (where <m>x</m> is a selected value).  The "=" in this case means something about convergence (which we will naively not concern ourselves with in this course). 
	</p>
	<p>
		The value of Taylor series is that we can use finite-degree polynomials to approximate our functions:
	</p>
	<me>f(x+\Delta x) \approx \sum_{k=0}^n \frac{f^{(k)}(x)}{k!}(\Delta x)^k</me>
	<p>
		The approximation above is called the <term><m>n</m>th order approximation</term>.  
	</p>
	<p>
		For small <m>n</m>, this can be calculated by hand.  For larger values of <m>n</m>, since there are still finitely many calculations involved, the approximation can be calculated by computers.  For us, we will be interested in <m>n = 1</m> or <m>n = 2</m>.
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="linear-and-higher-order-approximations">
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Let <m>P(\iota)</m> be the price (or present value) of some specific cash flows valued at a rate <m>\iota</m>.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Write an equation for the first order (linear) approximation for <m>P(\iota + \Delta \iota)</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Write an equation for the second order (quadratic) approximation for <m>P(\iota + \Delta \iota)</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="playing-with-the-exponential-function">
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Let's play with the function <m>f(x) = e^x</m>.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find the Taylor series around <m>x = 0</m>.  Since we have <m>x = 0</m>, just use <m>x</m> for <m>\Delta x</m>.  Note that this series converges for all <m>x</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Use your Taylor series to write down an expression for the number <m>e</m>, written as an infinite sum.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="playing-with-the-sin-function">
		<statement>
			<p>
				Let <m>f(x) = \sin(x)</m>.  Find the first order approximation around <m>x = 0</m>.  Since we have <m>x = 0</m>, just use <m>x</m> for <m>\Delta x</m>.  Note that the series converges for all <m>x</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="approximating-present-value">
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Recall that the present value of a perpetuity with a first payment of <m>K</m> whose payments grow by <m>100g \%</m> is given by the function:
			</p>
			<me>P(\iota) = \frac{K}{\iota - g}</me>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Suppose we have a share of stock that distributes annual dividends.  The first dividend is 2.50, and each dividend grows by 2% every year forever.  Let <m>P(\iota)</m> be the price of the share (using the dividend discount model) as a function of the effective annual interest rate <m>\iota</m>.  Write down <m>P(\iota)</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find the first-order (linear) approximation for <m>P(\iota + \Delta \iota)</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find the first-order (linear) approximation for <m>\Delta P = P(\iota + \Delta \iota) -  P(\iota)</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find the second-order (quadratic) approximation for <m>P(\iota + \Delta \iota)</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find the second-order (quadratic) approximation for <m>\Delta P</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="approximating-present-value-of-level-payment-annuity">
		<statement>
			<p>
				Let <m>P(\iota)</m> be the price (present value) of a level payment annuity with 10 annual payments of 125 using an effective annual interest rate of <m>\iota</m>.  Use the calculus of actuarial symbols to find the first-order (linear) approximation for <m>P(\iota + \Delta \iota)</m>.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="taylor-series-reflection">
		<statement>
			<p>
				What do Taylor series help us analyze for small perturbations in the interest rate?  What does this tell us about interest rate risk?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>
