<exercises xml:id="duration-and-convexity-exercises">
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				A zero coupon bond with a term of 5 years and maturity value of 1000 is purchased.  At the time the bond was purchased, the yield curve was <m>s_0(1) = 2.5\%</m>, <m>s_0(2) = 3.5\%</m>, <m>s_0(3) = 4\%</m>, <m>s_0(4) = 4.25\%</m>, and <m>s_0(5) = 4.3\%</m>. 
			</p>
			<p>
				Three years later, in the face of a possible recession, the yield curve inverts and \\ <m>s_3(1) = 5.5\%</m>, <m>s_3(2) = 4.5\%</m>, <m>s_3(3) = 4\%</m>, <m>s_3(4) = 4.25\%</m>, and <m>s_3(5) = 5.35\%</m>.  
			</p>
			<p>
				Compare the book and market values of the bond after three years and report the difference as a gain or a loss.                                                                        
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Suppose you have the following yield curve: 
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular halign="center" top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<m>t</m>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<m>s_0(t)</m>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							.34%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.01%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.79 %
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							4
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.34%
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
			<p>
				Consider a four-year bond with semiannual coupons, a coupon rate of 4.5%, and a face value of 1000.  
			</p>
			<p>
				For each year, determine the book and market value of the bond, given the yield curves that year.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				At the end of year 1, the yield curve is:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular halign="center" top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<m>t</m>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<m>s_1(t)</m>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							.67%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							6.80%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							7.15 %
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							4
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							7.32%
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				At the end of year 2, the yield curve is:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular halign="center" top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<m>t</m>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<m>s_2(t)</m>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							.12%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.92%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							6.39 %
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							4
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							7.21%
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				At the end of year 3, the yield curve is:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular halign="center" top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<m>t</m>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<m>s_3(t)</m>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							.87%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.23%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.46 %
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							4
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							5.72%
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				At the end of year 4, the yield curve is:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular halign="center" top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<m>t</m>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<m>s_4(t)</m>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							.89%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							4.11%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							4.43 %
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							4
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							4.50%
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				For each of the following cash flows, estimate whether the duration will be (i) closer to the beginning of the term, (ii) somewhere in the middle of the term, or (iii) closer to the end of the term.  Do not perform any calculations, just select on of the three options.  Justify your estimation.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Anticipated cash flows of 10,000 at the end of year 2, 150 at the end of year 3, and 500 at the end of year 10.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Anticipated cash flows of 750 each year for 4 years, 1000 each year for 3 years, and 900 at the end of year 8.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A zero-coupon bond.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A coupon bond.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A level-payment annuity.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				An increasing annuity.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A decreasing annuity.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Find the Macaulay duration for each of the following: 
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				A zero-coupon bond with maturity of 1000 in five years, priced to yield 3%.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A bond with semiannual coupons of 5% with a face value of 10,000 and a term of ten years, priced to yield 4.5%.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Anticipated cash flows of 10 million at the end of years 1, 2, 3, and 4, 12 million at the end of years 5 through 10, and a final payout of 20 million at the end of year 11.  The cash flows are priced to yield 5%.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A level payment annuity with quarterly payments of 2750 for 5 years, with <m>\iota^{(4)} = 1\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				An annuity with ten payments of 500, followed by two more payments of 1200, with <m>\iota = 6\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A 4-month monthly annuity with a first payment of 12,000, declining by 500 each month.  Assume <m>\iota^{(12)} = 9\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				An annual annuity with a first payment of 15,000, growing by 2.3% every year, for 3 years.  Assume <m>\iota = 4\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Cash flows of 1000 at the end of year 1, 1500 at the end of year 2, and 1150 at the end of year 3.  The yield curve is <m>s_0(1) = 5\%, s_0(2) = 6%</m>, and <m>s_0(3) = 6.5\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				In each of the following, convert from Macaulay duration to modified duration, or vice versa.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>D = 2.39</m>, <m>\iota = 4.36\%</m>
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>D = 9.81</m>, <m>\iota = 2.45\%</m>
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>MD = 7.51</m>, <m>\iota = 6.12\%</m>
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>MD = 12.23</m>, <m>\iota = 3.23\%</m>
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				<m>D =10.4</m>, <m>\iota = 5.50\%</m>
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Find the modified duration for each of the following:
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Projected cash flows of 10 million at the end of year 1, 8 million at the end of year 3, and 5 million at the end of year 4.  The effective annual interest rate is <m>\iota = 5.25\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A zero-coupon bond with a term of 20 years, a maturity value of 10,000, priced to yield 7%.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A coupon bond with a face value of 100, a semiannual coupon rate of 5%, a term of 15 years, priced to yield 6.5%.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A level-payment annuity with 10 payments of 1,500, valued at <m>\iota = 3.5\%.</m>
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A perpetuity-immediate with annual payments of 23,500.  The effective interest rate is <m>\iota = 1.5\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A perpetuity-due with annual payments of 19,500 and <m>d = 2.35\%</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Use modified duration to estimate the first order change in the present value of the following cash flows:
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				A project with projected cash flows of 1000 at the end of year 1, 2000 at the end of year 2, and 4000 at the end of year 3, originally priced to yield 10%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = 0.001</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A zero coupon bond with a term of 5 years, a maturity of 1000, priced to yield 5%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = -0.002</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A coupon bond with a term of 10 years, a semiannual coupon rate of 4%, a face value of 1000, originally priced to yield 6%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = 0.005</m>. 
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A level payment annuity with a term of 20 years, monthly payments of 50, priced to yield <m>\iota^{(12)} = 0.09</m>.  Set <m>\Delta \iota^{(12)} = -0.0012</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Use Macaulay approximation to estimate the change in the present value of the following cash flows:
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				A project with cash flows of 2000 at the end of year 1, 1000 at the end of year 2, and 3000 at the end of year 4. The project is priced to yield 8%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = -0.0035</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A zero coupon bond with a term of 4 years, a maturity of 1000, priced to yield 3.5%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = 0.009</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A coupon bond with a face value of 10,000, a semiannual coupon rate of 6%, a term of 15 years, priced to yield 5%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = - 0.01</m> where <m>\iota</m> is the effective semiannual interest rate.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A level payment annuity with a term of 7 years, quarterly payments of 150, priced to yield <m>\iota^{(2)} = 4\%</m>.  Set <m>\Delta \iota^{(2)} = 0.0055</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Use modified duration and convexity to estimate the second order change in the present value of the following cash flows:
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				A project with cash flows of 1000 at the end of year 1, 2000 at the end of year 2, and 3000 at the end of year 3.  The project is priced to yield 10%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = 0.01</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A zero coupon bond with a term of 10 years, a maturity value of 2500, priced to yield 6.5%.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = 0.005</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				A perpetuity-immediate with annual payments of 15,000, priced to yield <m>\iota = 9\%</m>.  Set <m>\Delta \iota = -0.003</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				A portfolio contains 30,000 worth of bonds with modified duration <m>MD = 3.96</m>; 20,000 worth of bonds with modified duration <m>MD = 4.08</m>; 40,000 worth of bonds with modified duration <m>MD = 1.69</m>; and 10,000 worth of zero-coupon bonds with a term of 10 years that are priced to yield 7%.  Find the modified duration of the portfolio.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<statement>
			<p>
				A portfolio contains 20,000 worth of bonds with duration <m>D = 5.46</m>; 40,000 worth of bonds with modified duration <m>MD = 6.71</m> priced to yield 5\%; and 20,000 worth of bonds with duration <m>D = 9.1</m>.  Find the Macaulay duration of the portfolio.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</exercise>
	<exercise>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Suppose investors face the following yield curve: 
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular halign="center" top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<m>t</m>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<m>s_0(t)</m>
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							2
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							6%
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							3
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							6.5%
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
			<p>
				Bond A has annual coupons at a rate of 5% for 3 years, and Bond B is a three-year zero coupon bond.  A portfolio <m>X</m> contains 30,000 worth of Bond A and 20,000 worth of Bond B.  
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find the Macaulay duration of the portfolio <m>X</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Find the modified duration of the portfolio <m>X</m>. For each of the bonds, use the flat effective annual yield rate that results in the prices you found above.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Use the modified duration to estimate the first order change in the value of <m>X</m> for a parallel shift in the yield curve of <m>\Delta \iota = -0.01</m>.
			</p>
		</task>
	</exercise>
</exercises>
