<section xml:id="ethics-audit-the-fed">
	<title>Ethics Case Study -- Audit the Fed</title>
	<p>
		Libertarians and some conservatives often call for legislation to audit the Federal Reserve.  While the Federal Reserve is subject to regular internal audits by independent inspectors general, external expert auditors, and more generally is subject to review by the Government Accountability Office, the calls to "audit the Fed" are based on seeking greater and more detailed Congressional oversight.  In effect, the creation of the central bank took the details of monetary policy out of democratic control.  By way of contrast, the details of fiscal policy (such as setting marginal tax rates and the federal budget) are entirely within Congress' control. 
	</p>
	<p>
		You are consulting an independent Senator on the Federal Reserve Transparency Act of 2015.  The legislation was passed by the House of Representatives, partly as a response to the 2008 financial crisis, and is now before the Senate.  You have been asked to consider whether voting for the bill is the ethical course of action.  
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-problem-statement">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 1</em>: State the Problem.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-fact-gathering">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 2</em>: Gather the Facts.
			</p>
			<p>
				Ben Bernanke was chair of the Federal Reserve Board of Governors from 2006 to 2014.  Read his analysis of the bill at <url href="https://bit.ly/BBAuditFed"/>. You can read the actual bill (although you might have to chase back references) at <url href="https://bit.ly/AuditFedBill"/>. One of the studies Bernanke cites is at <url href="https://bit.ly/FedStudyDomestic"/>, and another (which analyzes the impact of central banking on countries transitioning away from communism) can be accessed at <url href="https://bit.ly/AuditFedTransition"/>.  
			</p>
			<p>
				Summarize your findings and state your starting position.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-identify-stakeholders">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 3</em>: Identify stakeholders.  Consider both primary stakeholders (directly affected) and secondary stakeholders (indirectly affected).  Try to see the situation through the eyes of all possible stakeholders. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-develop-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 4</em>: Develop options.  Be imaginative, avoid dilemmas or yes/no situations. Instead consider how to modify questions and ask “to/for whom” or “how much." 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-test-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 5</em>: Test options by determining how the stakeholders you identified are harmed or benefited by an action or inaction.  Test at least two options by filling in the following tables.  You can add rows for more stakeholders, and make additional tables for more options. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<em>Option 1</em>:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Stakeholder
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Primary or Secondary?
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Harms
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Benefits
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<line>

							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-make-decision">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 6</em>: Make a decision. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-check-work">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 7</em>: Check your work!  Make sure your decision follows your gut instincts and your internal principles.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="audit-the-fed-memo">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Write a memo to the Senator with a recommendation.  Be sure to support your position and address counterarguments.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>