<introduction>
	<p>
		When a company raises funds (called <term>capital</term>) to invest in its business operations, they have two options: equity and debt.   Equity involves raising funds by offering investors a share of ownership of the company.  Equity investors are not legally entitled to payments -- they take all of the risks of the company.  When a company is publicly traded, they issue shares of ownership through stocks that can be freely traded on "secondary markets" like the New York Stock Exchange. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Debt differs from equity in that debt-holders are not owners of the company, they do not take the risks that come with ownership, and they are compensated for any risks they take through the payment of interest. Debt holders are legally entitled to payment.
	</p>
	<p>
		The best illustration of the difference between debt and equity is what happens in a liquidation bankruptcy.  If a company can no longer pay its bills or operate its business, they can file for bankruptcy.  One form of bankruptcy - the most drastic - is liquidation: selling off all of the company's assets, using the proceeds to pay off any debts, and going out of existence.  In such a case, the proceeds of the are distributed according to a statutory priority scheme.  Priority goes to anyone with a legal claim, such as employees, lawyers, creditors, and debt-holders.  Equity investors get their share of whatever is left, which may be nothing.  This process is supervised by a federal judge in bankruptcy court. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The typical example of debt financing is a loan, as we studied in the last chapter.  Unlike shares of stock, it is difficult to buy and sell loans and there is no standard secondary market. 
	</p>
	<p>
		A <term>bond</term> is a hybrid of debt and equity.  Bonds are sold by a company raising money, called the <term>issuer</term>, and bought by investors called <term>bondholders</term>.  A bond is a loan -- bondholders are legally entitled to their payments and have a place of priority in the U.S. Bankruptcy Code.  Unlike a loan, the legal terms of bonds are standardized, and loans can and are bought and sold on secondary markets.  In that way, they have some of the advantages of stocks, with less risk. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Bonds are also issued by governments.  The federal government issues treasury bonds, often considered "risk-free" since governments can always print money to pay their bondholders. 
		\newpage
		\thispagestyle{plain}
		Municipal governments and local school districts also issue bonds frequently.  You may have even been asked to vote to approve a bond offering for a school district.  The interest on municipal  bonds is exempt from income taxation. 
	</p>
	<p>
		The way a bond works is that the issuer pays the bondholders interest payments (called <term>coupon payments</term>) periodically, and then repay the principal with the final coupon payment. The price of the bond is the present value of the payments at a rate called the <term>yield rate</term>. 
	</p>
</introduction>
