<section xml:id="ethics-enron">
	<title>Ethics Case Study -- Enron and Mark-to-Market Accounting</title>
	<p>
		At the end of 2001, Enron filed for bankruptcy (represented by Weil, Gotshal, and Manges - my old law firm).  At the time, this was the largest bankruptcy in history, and was a shock to the U.S. economy.  The Enron bankruptcy revealed a significant accounting scandal that brought down Arthur Andersen, one of the "big 5" accounting firms. In 2002, Congress responses by passing the Sarbanes-Oxley Act. 
	</p>
	<p>
		So what happened?  One of the significant causes of the bankruptcy and scandal concerned Enron's mark-to-market accounting (which requires permission from the Securities and Exchange Commission).  Under <term>mark-to-market accounting</term>, firms can report the fair market value of their assets in their accounting filings.  Since this can be difficult to ascertain, a common approach is to use the net present value of projected future cash flows.  Enron founder and chair Ken Lay, CEO Jeffrey Skilling, and CFO Andrew Fastow assured the public and investors that their estimates were credible.  In reality, the cash flows ended up much lower than predicted, often leading to losses.  One of the most infamous was a mid-90s deal with the Blockbuster video rental chain to provide content streaming services, but the technology was not ready and the project failed.  
	</p>
	<p>
		Enron handled these losses by creating <term>special purpose entities</term> - subsidiary corporations that exist for a single purpose - to assume the losses from the various projects.  That way, the losses Enron suffered were hidden from Enron's filings and hidden from investors. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Suppose you work at an actuarial firm.  You are reviewing the firm's investment portfolio.  You find significant investment in a single very large company called Reliant, Inc.  Reliant invests in projects all over the world, and uses mark-to-market accounting to report income from these projects.  You notice that Reliant has had tremendous luck, as none of the projects have ever caused any losses to Reliant.  This sounds fishy to you -- surely some will have high returns and others will be disappointments!  
	</p>
	<p>
		You bring this to your department chair, who waves it away.  When you insist, the partner discloses to you in confidence that the CEO is a close relative of your firm's managing partner.  Several partners, including your department chair, already tried to talk the managing partner of the risk of investing in Reliant.  The managing partner would not budge, eventually threatening to dissolve some of the partners of their role in the firm (in effect, firing them).  Some partners suspect that the managing partner is receiving kickbacks.  You are urged to let this matter go. 
	</p>
	<p>
		You return to your office to think through this carefully, working through our ethical decision framework.  Once you decide what you want to do, you plan on writing a memo to yourself to file away as evidence in case you have to defend yourself, whether to your boss, prosecutors, or the public.  (In the professional environments, these kinds of memos are called "memos to the files").
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="enron-problem-statement">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 1</em>: State the Problem.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="enron-fact-gathering">
		<introduction>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 2</em>: Gather the Facts.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Let's look at an example of mark-to-market accounting.  Suppose Reliant enters a deal that will require an initial investment of 1.25 million today.  They project that this deal will result in cash flows of 2.5 million at the end of each of the next three years, 2 million at the end of each of the following 2 years, and 1 million at the end of the following year.  The project terminates after that point.  Find the <m>NPV</m> at 4% annually.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				In reality, the project generates cash flows of 250,000 at the end of the first three years, 200,000 at the end of the following two years, and 100,000 at the end of the following year (after which the project terminates).  Find the actual <m>NPV</m> at 4%.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Since the projected <m>NPV</m> is reported as income for Reliant in their filings, the difference between the projected and actual <m>NPV</m> is a loss.  These are the losses Enron hid in their off-book special purpose entities.  
			</p>
			<p>
				Moreover, with the losses stuffed away off Reliant's books, Reliant will need new sources of income every year (or quarter, or other appropriate recording period).  How does this distort Reliant managers'\ incentives and create an unsustainable cycle?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="enron-identify-stakeholders">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 3</em>: Identify stakeholders.  Consider both primary stakeholders (directly affected) and secondary stakeholders (indirectly affected).  Try to see the situation through the eyes of all possible stakeholders. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="enron-develop-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 4</em>: Develop options.  Be imaginative, avoid dilemmas or yes/no situations. Instead consider how to modify questions and ask “to/for whom” or “how much." 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="enron-test-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 5</em>: Test options by determining how the stakeholders you identified are harmed or benefited by an action or inaction.  Test at least two options by filling in the following tables.  You can add rows for more stakeholders, and make additional tables for more options. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<em>Option 1</em>:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Stakeholder
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Primary or Secondary?
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Harms
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Benefits
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<line>

							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="enron-make-decision">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 6</em>: Make a decision. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="enron-check-work">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 7</em>: Check your work!  Make sure your decision follows your gut instincts and your internal principles.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="enron-memo">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Write a memo to the files stating and defending your position.  Be sure to support your position and address counterarguments (see outline in <xref ref="ethics-student-loans-and-covid"/>).
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>