<section xml:id="ethics-payday-loans">
	<title>Ethics Case Study -- Payday Loans</title>
	<p>
		<term>Payday loans</term> are short-term loans that are designed to be paid back after receiving a paycheck.  The borrower writes a post-dated check to the lender for the amount to be paid back including interest (called "fees"), and the check has to be dated no more than two weeks after the funds are dispersed. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Interest rates on payday loans tend to be very high.  Consumer advocates consider them predatory, and lobby for them to be outlawed or heavily regulated.  In Michigan, payday loans are allowed and authorized by statute (MCL Section 487.2121).  Currently, sixteen states and the District of Columbia outlaw high-cost payday loans. 
	</p>
	<p>
		Let's follow our ethical decision making process to analyze this.
	</p>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-problem-statement">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 1</em>: State the Problem.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-fact-gathering">
		<introduction>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 2</em>: Gather the Facts.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Visit the website for the loan terms at All-Star Payday Loans: 
			</p>
			<p>
				<url href="https://www.allstarpaydayloans.com/loan-terms"/>
			</p>
			<p>
				All-Star is a payday lender in Big Rapids, Manistee, and Rockford (all in Michigan). 
			</p>
			<p>
				For each loan amount, determine the effective annual interest rate charged.  Remember that these are 2-week loans.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>	
			<p> 
				Consider a borrower who has medical debt to pay, or a student who has to make a tuition payment to unlock a registration hold.  They borrow from All-Star, and possibly borrow from several other payday lenders around town in order to accumulate what they need.  What happens in two weeks, when they get paid by their employer but the lender cashes their post-dated check?  What could happen long-term for such a borrower?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-identify-stakeholders">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 3</em>: Identify stakeholders.  Consider both primary stakeholders (directly affected) and secondary stakeholders (indirectly affected).  Try to see the situation through the eyes of all possible stakeholders. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-develop-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 4</em>: Develop options.  Be imaginative, avoid dilemmas or yes/no situations. Instead consider how to modify questions and ask “to/for whom” or “how much." 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-test-options">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 5</em>: Test options by determining how the stakeholders you identified are harmed or benefited by an action or inaction.  Test at least two options by filling in the following tables.  You can add rows for more stakeholders, and make additional tables for more options. 
			</p>
			<p>
				<em>Option 1</em>:
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Stakeholder
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Primary or Secondary?
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Harms
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Benefits
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<line>

							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-make-decision">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 6</em>: Make a decision. 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-check-work">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				<em>Step 7</em>: Check your work!  Make sure your decision follows your gut instincts and your internal principles.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="payday-loans-memo">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Write a memo setting forth and defending a recommendation to Governor Eisler of the State of Ferris.  Be sure to support your position and address counterarguments (see outline in <xref ref="ethics-student-loans-and-covid"/>).
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>