<section xml:id="annuities-valued-at-other-times">
	<title>Annuity Valuations at Other Points in Time</title>
	<p>
		In the last activity we met deferred annuities.  This was an example of valuing an annuity (or perpetuity) at various points on the timeline.  In general, we push our present/future values forward or pull them backward along the timeline to the point where we want to value. 
	</p>
	<assemblage>
		<title>&#x1F9EE; Calculator Tip </title>
		<p> 
			As  with deferred annuities, you can use the financial calculators to value an annuity at any point in time.  As needed, calculate the future or present value, then hit either the <kbd>PV</kbd> or <kbd>FV</kbd> button (depending on if you are pulling back or pushing forward), make <kbd>PMT</kbd> 0, and change the value for <kbd>N</kbd>.  If needed, you may also have to change <kbd>I/Y</kbd> if the rate changes (although we will deal more with that in <xref ref="chunking"/>).
		</p> 
	</assemblage>
	<activity xml:id="finding-values-at-other-times">
		<introduction>
			<p> 
				Payments of 100 per quarter are made from June 7, Z (Z is the year) through December 7, Z+11, inclusive. If the nominal rate of interest convertible quarterly is 6%:
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Find the present value on September 7, Z-1.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Find the current value on March 7, Z+8. 
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p> 
				Find the accumulated value on June 7, Z+ 12.
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="valuing-annuity-before-end">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Logan Roy has gifted an annuity to his grandnephew Greg Hirsch.  The annuity pays 3 million per year for 10 years, starting at the end of this year.  Greg deposits each payment into an account earning an effective annual interest rate of <m>\iota = 3\%</m>.  Sixteen years from today (six  years after the last payment), Greg wants to purchase a small, progressive newspaper for 45 million.  How much is in the account at this point?  How much additional funding would he need to make the purchase?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="valuing-annuity-before-start">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Suppose Siobhan Roy purchases an annuity that pays 5 million per year for 15 years, but starting 5 years from the time of purchase.  The annuity is valued at an effective annual interest rate of <m>\iota = 5\%</m>.  If Siobhan purchased the annuity today, what did she pay for it? 
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity xml:id="valuing-annuities-at-other-times-reflection">
		<statement>
			<p> 
				Describe how we value annuities at different points in time.  What do you think will be tricky?
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>
