<section xml:id="ethics-student-loans">
	<title>Ethics Case Study: Student Loans</title>
	<p>
		When the National Defense Education Act established federal student loans in 1958, it included a percentage reduction in a borrower's loan for each year they spent teaching. Since then, multiple policies to ease the burden of student loans have been discussed and implemented, including loan forgiveness and subsidizing the interest on each loan.
	</p>
	<p>
		The ethics of student loans has been debated for as long as they have been offered. Some people argue that you should pay back what you borrow; others argue that steps should be taken to make sure student loans are not unduly burdensome. In this activity, we'll explore the ethics of subsidizing student loan interest.
	</p>
	<activity>
		<task>
			<p>
				Before we start, read about the six <term>ethical lenses</term> published by the <url href="https://www.scu.edu/ethics/ethics-resources/a-framework-for-ethical-decision-making/">Markkula Center for Applied Ethics at Santa Clara University</url>. Which lens(es) do you think you will bring to this analysis?
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Read about the <url href="https://www.federalreserve.gov/publications/2025-economic-well-being-of-us-households-in-2024-higher-education-and-student-loans.htm">student debt burden at the Federal Reserve's website</url>. Which statistic (or statistics) surprises you the most? 
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Read about the types of federal student loans at <url href="https://studentaid.gov/understand-aid/types/loans">studentaid.gov</url>. What is the difference between a Direct Subsidized Loan and a Direct Unsubsidized Loan? What is your initial assessment of the advantages and disadvantages of each for the borrower?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity>
		<introduction>
			<p>
				Let's look at an example. Student A takes out the maximum in Direct Subsidized Loans each year for four years: $3,500, $4,500, $5,500, and $5,500. Student B takes out equivalent amounts in Direct Unsubsidized Loans. 
			</p>
			<p>
				The rate as of this writing is 6.39% effective annual for the life of the loan, compounded monthly. For simplicity, let's assume that the same interest rate applies to each of the four loans taken out by each student.
			</p>
		</introduction>
		<task>
			<p>
				Create a timeline for the loan disbursements for each student through June 1 at the end of their fourth year of college; assume each of them receives the disbursement on September 1 of the relevant year and that the student with the unsubsidized loan *capitalizes* their interest by rolling their interest payments into the principal.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Determine the accumulated value of each of their loans on June 1 of the end of their fourth year of college.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Assume each borrower agrees to a 15-year repayment plan on that day. How much will each one owe each month?
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Now assume that each of Student A and B enroll in a 2-year graduate program and that their loans are deferred for another 2 years. Student B's loan will continue to accumulate interest over this time and, once again, they capitalize their interest. If they agree to a repayment plan on June 1 of the year they finish their graduate programs, how much will each one owe each month?
			</p>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity>
		<task>
			<p>
				You are on the staff of a U.S. representative who serves on the Education and Workforce Committee. A discussion of the types of student loans is on the agenda for the next meeting, and you have been asked to come up with three proposed ways to structure federal subsidized and unsubsidized loan offerings and submit a memo with an analysis of each of them and a recommendation for the one you think is most appropriate.
			</p>
		</task>
		<task>
			<p>
				Let’s do a stakeholder analysis. Make a list of all those who would be impacted by implementing the structures you are considering. Include both primary stakeholders (directly affected) and secondary stakeholders (indirectly affected). Try to see the situation through the eyes of all possible stakeholders.
			</p>
			<p>
				Test your options by determining how the stakeholders you identified are harmed or benefited by implementing or not implementing these structures. Test options by filling in the following tables. You can add rows for more stakeholders and make additional tables for more options.
			</p>
			<table>
				<tabular top="medium">
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							Stakeholder
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Primary or Secondary?
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Harms
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							Benefits
						</cell>
					</row>
					<row bottom="medium">
						<cell left="medium" right="medium">
							<line>

							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
						<cell right="medium">
							<line>
							</line>
						</cell>
					</row>
				</tabular>
			</table>
		</task>
	</activity>
	<activity>
		<statement>
			<p>
				Make a decision: write a memo to the representative you work for explaining and analyzing your three proposed structures. State your recommendation first, and then justify your decision with explicit reference to the stakeholder analysis.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
	<activity>
		<statement>
			<p>
				Finally, reflect on your decision. What was the nature of your justification? Look back at the ethical lenses from Santa Clara University. Which lens(es) best fit your recommendation? Was that the same or different from what you identified at the beginning of this activity? Does that surprise you? Why or why not? Write a brief paragraph responding to these questions and include it with your memo.
			</p>
		</statement>
	</activity>
</section>