<section xml:id="annuities-with-geometric-progressions-complications">
	<title>Annuities with Payments in Geometric Progression 3 -- Further Problems</title>
	<introduction>
		<p>
			We will conclude our discussion of annuities with payments in geometric progression with a few miscellaneous matters that round out the subject.  In this activity, we will address:
		</p>
		<ul>
			<li>
				<p> 
					Using annuities to create a theoretical price for a share of stock;
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p> 
					Valuing annuities where the payment frequency and the frequency of changes in the payments are different; and
				</p>
			</li>
			<li>
				<p> 
					Identifying how the real interest rate <m>\iota_{\mathrm{real}}</m> can play a role.
				</p>
			</li>
		</ul>
	</introduction>
	<subsection xml:id="dividend-discount-model-for-valuing-stacks">
		<title>The Dividend Discount Model for Valuing Stock</title>
		<p>
			Valuing shares of stock is highly nontrivial, and our best methods are built on serious assumptions that some find problematic.  You will see more of this in future exams like IFM.  
		</p>
		<p>
			For now, we are going to find a "theoretical price" for a share of stock by viewing the stock as a set of cash flows, namely, their dividends.  This is not a realistic assumption, as companies are never guaranteed to distribute dividend payments (and even if they do, it is rarely predictable in advance).  Nevertheless, using the cash flow generated by future dividends provides a nice application of annuities.
		</p>
		<activity xml:id="theoretical-price-formulas-for-stock">
			<introduction>
				<p> 
					Let's start by finding these theoretical price formulas.
				</p>
			</introduction>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Suppose we know that a company is going to issue periodic dividends of <m>D</m>.  The periodic interest rate is <m>\iota</m>.  Find a formula for the present value, which is the theoretical price of the stock.
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Now suppose that the next dividend is <m>D</m>, and each subsequent dividend grows by a constant percentage <m>r</m>.  Find the formula for the theoretical price.
				</p>
			</task>
		</activity>
		<activity xml:id="using-theoretical-price-formulas-for-stocks">
			<introduction>
				<p> 
					Use your models for the following exercises.
				</p>
			</introduction>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Find the theoretical price of a stock that pays an annual dividend of 4.5.  The effective annual interest rate is 2.25%. 
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Find the theoretical price of a stock will pay a quarterly dividend.  The first dividend will be paid 1 year from now, and will be 10.  Each dividend will grow by 3%.  The effective quarterly interest rate is 4%. 
				</p>
			</task>
		</activity>
		<activity xml:id="theoretical-price-formulas-for-stock-soa">
			<statement>
				<p> 
					A share of James Brown Inc (JBI) is trading for 125.  The company issues annual dividends.  The dividend at the end of this year will be 5, and each subsequent dividend will be 3% larger.  What effective annual interest rate is implied by this price?
				</p>
			</statement>
		</activity> 
	</subsection>
	<subsection xml:id="different-payments-and-geometric-frequencies">
		<title>Different Payment and Geometric Frequencies</title>
		<p>
			Sometimes the frequency of the payments does not match the frequency of the percentage changes in the payments.  For example, it is common to have pension payments given monthly, but adjusted for cost of living annually based on the CPI.  The following former exam problem illustrates this. 
		</p>
		<activity xml:id="payments-with-frequencies-that-change-with-irregular-frequency">
			<introduction>
				<p> 
					Stan elects to receive his retirement benefit over 20 years at the rate of 2000 per month beginning one month from now. The monthly benefit increases by 5% each year. At a nominal interest rate of 6% convertible monthly, calculate the present value of the retirement benefit.
				</p>
			</introduction>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Generate a timeline.
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					The strategy to solve this is going to be to "annualize" the annuity by finding an equivalent sequence of payments that occur at the same frequency as the percentage changes. 
				</p>
				<p>
					To this end, find an expression for the value of the first 12 payments.  Do not evaluate the expression, just write it down.  (You choose when to value)
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Find an expression for the value of the second 12 payments (payments 13 through 24).  Do not evaluate the expression, just write it down. 
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					One more time! Find an expression for the value of the third set of 12 payments (payments 25 through 36).  Do not evaluate the expression, just write it down.
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					What do you notice about your expressions? 
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					If we were to want to find an equivalent annuity but with <term>annual</term> payments (in geometric progression), what would the payments be? Do not evaluate, leave each payment as an expression (and you do not have to write all 20 expressions down!).
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Let us fix the details.  For the chunks of 12 payments, what interest rate should you use?  What about for valuing the full annuity?  
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					With all of this set-up, solve the problem.
				</p>
			</task>
		</activity>
		<activity xml:id="mixed-frequencies-strategy">
			<statement>
				<p> 
					Describe the strategy we used.  What other choice could we have made to solve the problem?
				</p>
			</statement>
		</activity>
	</subsection>
	<subsection xml:id="using-iota-real">
		<title>Using <m>\iota_{\mathrm{real}}</m> </title>
		<p>
			In <xref ref="compound-interest-and-timeline-reasoning"/>, we saw that we can adjust the effective interest rate <m>\iota</m> to deal with the impact of an inflation rate <m>r</m>, in which case we had:
		</p>
		<me>1+\iota_{\mathrm{real}} = \frac{1+\iota}{1+r}</me>
		<p>
			Solving for the rate itself, we can simplify to get:
		</p>
		<me>\iota_{\mathrm{real}} = \frac{\iota-r}{1+r}</me>
		<p>
			Now suppose <m>r</m> is the percentage rate at which the payments of an annuity increase.  Can we leverage <m>\iota_{\mathrm{real}}</m> to make this easier?
		</p>
		<activity xml:id="example-using-iota-real">
			<introduction>
				<p> 
					Let's see how the use of <m>\iota_{\mathrm{real}}</m> impacts our annuity formulas.
				</p>
			</introduction>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Find a formula for <m>a_{\angln \iota_{\mathrm{real}}}</m>.  Compare your result to our formula for the present value of an annuity with payments in geometric progression.
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					Find a formula for <m>s_{\angln \iota_{\mathrm{real}}}</m>.  Compare your result to our formula for the accumulated value of an annuity with payments in geometric progression.
				</p>
			</task>
		</activity>
		<activity xml:id="solving-problems-using-iota-real">
			<statement>
				<p> 
					Solve the following, using <m>\iota_{\mathrm{real}}</m>.
				</p>
			</statement>
			<task>
				<p> 
					An annuity-immediate has 15 annual payments.  The first is 1000, and each subsequent payment grows by 3%.  The effective annual interest rate is <m>\iota = 5\%</m>.  Find the present value.
				</p>
			</task>
			<task>
				<p> 
					An annuity-immediate has 10 annual payments.  The first is 200, and each subsequent payment grows by 2%.  The effective annual interest rate is <m>\iota = 3\%</m>.  Find the accumulated value.
				</p>
			</task>
		</activity>
		<activity xml:id="iota-real-reflection">
			<task>
				<p> 
					Do you prefer using <m>\iota_{\mathrm{real}}</m> or the formulas from <xref ref="annuities-with-payments-in-geometric-progression-the-short-way"/>?  Why? 
				</p>
			</task>
		</activity>
	</subsection>
</section>